Finding Aid for Wilfrid de St. Aubin Papers 1938-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Wilfrid de St. Aubin Papers 1938-1980
St. Aubin, Wilfrid de, 1902-1980.
1 oversize folder
7 linear feet
Executive with the American Red Cross. Correspondence, diaries, reports, memoranda, and other materials relating to relief and refugee work during World War II in Italy, France, and Germany (Buchenwald), his work in re-establishing Red Cross societies in Austria, Hungary, and the Middle East after the war, and his survey of humanitarian problems resulting from the Palestinian conflict, 1948.
85495 Aa 2 UAm
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Ethel de St. Aubin (donor no. 6600 ) and came to the library in 1981 and 1982.
The collection is open for research.
Wilfrid de St. Aubin was born in Chicago, Illinois on November 24, 1902. He was educated at Notre Dame University and the Chicago-Kent College of Law. During the depression, he worked for various relief agencies in Indiana and Washington DC.
It was during World War II that St. Aubin first began his association with the American Red Cross. In September 1943, he was appointed field representative for the American Red Cross Civilian War Relief program in Italy, France and Germany. His responsibilities centered around the distribution of relief supplies to civilians, the evacuation of these civilians, and the establishment of hospitals in combat areas. During the later period of the war, St. Aubin supervised welfare programs at Buchenwald.
In 1945, St. Aubin became director of the Red Cross Civilian Relief program in Austria where he was concerned with relief and rehabilitation and where he helped re-establish the Red Cross society of that country. In 1947, he moved on to Hungary where he performed similar functions. During this time, he also carried out Red Cross missions in Czechoslovakia and Yugoslavia.
In 1948, St. Aubin was appointed Delegate of the League of Red Cross Societies to the Middle East. Here he surveyed and advised national Red Cross and Red Crescent societies in Iran, Syria, Lebanon, Jordan, Israel, Greece, Egypt, and Ethiopia. During part of this time, St. Aubin was attached to the staff of Count Folke Bernadotte, United Nations Mediator for Palestine. He surveyed the humanitarian problems of the Palestinian conflict, and was a special consultant on the needs of the refugees.
In 1949, St. Aubin became supervisor for International Agency Relations of the American National Red Cross. During the Korean War, he was on an advisory committee on the prisoner of war situation. In 1955, he was appointed executive director of the Washtenaw County chapter of the American Red Cross. He retired from this position in 1969.
Beyond the Red Cross, St. Aubin was involved in a variety of charitable and public service organizations, notably the American Overseas Association, the National Council of Christians and Jews, the Washtenaw County Interfaith Council of Churches, and Spaulding for Children (an adoption agency).
Wilfrid de St. Aubin died November 2, 1980.
The Wilfrid de St. Aubin collection consists of seven feet of correspondence, reports, memoranda, and other official papers covering his Red Cross work during World War II and the immediate postwar period. Of special interest is a letter and report written by St. Aubin containing his impression and observations of the Buchenwald concentration camp. St. Aubin was one of the first to come to the camp after its liberation. There are also diaries which provide added background and detail of St. Aubin's varied career.
Subjects:
American National Red Cross.; Austria.; Buchenwald (Concentration camp); Concentration camps.; France.; Hungary.; Italy.; Middle East.; Palestine.; Red Cross.; Refugees.; St. Aubin, Wilfrid de, 1902-1980.; World War, 1939-1945--War work--Red Cross.
Subjects - Visual Material:
American National Red Cross.; American National Red Cross. Washtenaw County Chapter.; Austria.; Children.; Concentration camps.; Costumes, Austrian.; Death.; Egypt.; Handicapped persons--Health and welfare.; Hospitals.; Hungary.; Japan.; Korean War, 1950-1953.; Military personnel.; Palestine.; Refugees.; St. Aubin, Wilfrid de, 1902-1980.; War damage.; War relief.; Women--War.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Personnel file (Box 1)
    (including employment records, salary materials, and job evaluations)
  - Commendations, awards, and personal miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Collected letters concerning the Modern Historic Records Association 1911-1912 (Box 1)
    (include letters from Woodrow Wilson, Theodore Roosevelt, James Bryce, John Barrett, and Hiram Maxim)
  - Diaries, personal ledgers, and jotting books circa 1944-1956, 2 expandable folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence and other papers
  - 1938-1943 (Box 1)
  - 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - 1948-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951-1954 (Box 1)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1967 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Julius Vallay (director-general of the Hungarian Red Cross) (Box 1)
  - Retirement letters and clippings 1968, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Ethel Atkinson to Wilfrid de St. Aubin 1954, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Wilfrid de St. Aubin to Ethel Atkinson 1954, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Ethel Atkinson to Wilfrid de St. Aubin 1955, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Wilfrid de St. Aubin to Ethel Atkinson 1955, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Wilfrid de St. Aubin to Ethel Atkinson 1956 (Box 1)
  - Ethel Atkinson to Wilfrid de St. Aubin 1956 (Box 1)
- Red Cross
  - World War II
    - Summary of activities: Civilian War Relief (Box 2)
    - Memoranda: Civilian War Relief (Box 2)
    - Instructions and orders (Box 2)
    - Italian front: memoranda, reports, etc. re. hospitals (Box 2)
    - Italian front: memoranda, reports, etc. concerning civilian war relief (Box 2)
    - Italian front: miscellanea (Box 2)
    - Field vouchers (Box 2)
    - Southern France: memoranda, reports, etc (Box 2)
    - Buchenwald: letter and report (Box 2)
    - Ninth Army: memoranda re. civilian war relief (Box 2)
  - Post-War
    - General
      - Reports of operations (Box 2)
      - Supervisor's reports (Box 2)
    - Austria
      - Memoranda and letters re. civilian war relief (Box 2)
      - Reports re. civilian war relief (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Hungary
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
      - Reports, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Distribution plans, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Czechoslovakia
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - League of Red Cross Societies to the Middle East
    - Miscellaneous field survey material (Box 2)
    - Recommendations (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Ethiopia (Box 2)
    - Greece (Box 2)
    - Iran, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Lebanon (Box 2)
    - Palestine
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Reports, memoranda, etc., 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Syria (Box 3)
    - Trans-Jordan (Box 3)
    - Turkey (Box 3)
  - American Red Cross
    - Correspondence 1949-1950 (Box 3)
  - Red Cross in Korea
    - Report 1953 (Box 3)
  - Red Cross, Washtenaw County
    - Papers (Box 3)
- Other Organizational Activities
  - American Overseas Association
    - Papers 1949-1977, 12 folders (Box 3)
    - Topical files
      - Letters from Association president (Box 3)
      - Memorial committee papers, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Lists of officers and members (Box 3)
      - Harold Condict correspondence and papers (Box 3)
    - Printed material (Box 3)
  - Interfaith Council of Churches
    - Dental care program (for low-income children of Washtenaw County) 1971-1973 (Box 4)
  - National Council of Christians and Jews
    - Papers 1956-1970, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - Topical files
      - Board lists (Box 4)
      - Round Table 1965-1970 (Box 4)
      - Brotherhood Banquet 1961-1967 (Box 4)
      - Kahn Memorial Projects, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Spaulding for Children
    - Papers
      - 1972-1976 (Box 4)
      - 1978 (Box 4)
      - 1979 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Annual reports and printed matter (Box 4)
- Articles, speeches, and other miscellaneous
  - Articles and other writings, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Speeches 1948-1969, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Huron Valley Toastmasters Club (Box 5)
  - Speech notes, drafts, and miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Reference materials for speeches, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Red Cross printed material (Box 5)
  - Personal letters from his mother, brothers and sisters, and friends 1940s (Box 5)
  - Papers relating to family trust (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook, re. Hammond housing survey 1934-1935 (Box 5)
- Washtenaw County Council on Aging
  - General
    - 1972-1980, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - Minutes (primarily board of directors and executive committee)
    - 1972-1980, 9 folders (Box 6)
  - Tax Aid Project
    - General 1973-1980, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Minutes 1974-1980 (Box 6)
  - Senior Reporter (newsletter)
    - 1974-1980, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Retired Senior Volunteer Program (RSVP)
    - General (scattered dates), 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Senior Scribbles (newsletter) 1974-1980, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Aging (miscellaneous)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 6)
    - Michigan White House Conference on Aging 1971, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor Planning Committee for Lifelong Learning 1969 (Box 6)
    - Institute of Gerontology Conference on Economics of Aging 1975 (Box 6)
    - Printed matter re. aging, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Photographs
  (see also oversize folder, UAm)
  - Africa, Egypt (Box 7)
  - Austria (Box 7)
  - Children's Christmas Party, Vienna (Box 7)
  - Friends and Colleagues (Box 7)
  - Groups (Box 7)
  - Hungary (Box 7)
  - Italy 1948 (Box 7)
  - Japan (Box 7)
  - Korea, POW efforts (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Portraits (Box 7)
  - Palestine, Middle East (Box 7)
  - Red Cross groups and headquarters (Box 7)
  - Snapshots of St. Aubin (Box 7)
  - Washtenaw County Chapter and retirement photos 1968 (Box 7)
  - Albums, 4 volumes
    - Farewell party, Vienna 1946 (Box 7)
    - Farewell party, Vienna 1946 Christmas party, Vienna, 1946 (Box 7)
    - Elisabeth Hospital of the Hungarian Red Cross (Box 7)
    - Crippled Children's Home in Budapest (Box 7)